So, now that you've learned to program a
microprocessor from the 1970s, I'd like to take a
quick fast forward from the 1970s to the present.
A lot's changed since the 6502 was available as a
$25 microprocessor. Since the 1970s, there have
been about 50 distinct CPU families. I've been
part of this my whole career. Lots of research
and innovation adoption switching computer vendors
picking one CPU and then switching to another
CPU. Generational turnover and overall approach
from complex instruction sets to simpler risk
instruction sets from large refrigerator size
mainframes to to micro small microprocessors then
larger microprocessors faster microprocessors.
Interestingly, after all that, things have
settled down in the modern era. There are
two major CPU families in use. If you think
about consumer uh and server and desktop,
if you take computers and phones and bring
them together, about 90% of the marketplace
is ARMbased processors and the remaining 10% is
Intel processors. ARM is very successful because
it was focused on low power. And as computers have
gotten faster and faster, uh we really care more
and more about saving power u both for uh small
handheld devices and for uh desktops and then even
laptops. And so power savings is really important
and the ARM was designed to save power. So let's
take a quick case study and look at uh Apple over
the over the years. Uh Apple the Apple 1 was one
of the early adopters of the 6502. um in 1997 and
the and the Apple 2 and the Apple 2 and its sort
of whole family were a very successful set of
microprocessors for a long time. Apple switched
to a different processor, the Motorola 68000
from 1984 to 1994. During that time, they were
playing with a project called the Newton, which
was a handheld device. Wasn't extremely popular,
but it was a handheld device. um battery powered
handheld sort of pocket but that was using an ARM
processor an ARM processor. Then I then they
switched from the Motorola to the Power PC
in 1994 and again 12 more years they use the
Power PC and then the Intel x86 in 2006. They
switched their Macintosh line from using Power PC
to Intel x86. I was actually in the audience when
Steve Jobs announced the switch from Power PC to
Intel 8 x86. I was I was amazed. I I was sitting
I was working on my laptop which had a Power PC
in it. I've been using it for years and at the
end he threw the doors open and we ran into some
rooms and there were some prototype uh Intel x86.
Macintosh is running Mac OS and it was amazing to
me that they could switch from Power PC to Intel
x86. Then the iPhone came out in 2007 and I was
also in the audience when Steve Jobs announced the
first iPhone, this iPhone 1. And I was carrying
around at that point in time, I was carrying
around a a trio as my main computer. And the trio
was one of the things he put up on the screen when
uh he was talking about the iPhone, but the iPhone
had an ARM, a Samsung ARM in it. And so this is an
ARM processor. And then 20 in 2020 the ARM came
not just to the iPhone but from the Macintosh.
ARM is not manufactured by one organization. The
ARM is licensed to many folks to build them and
Apple builds its own hardware in the Macintosh
from 2020 to present. And what's interesting
about that is Apple is currently redesigning
their CPUs continuously. Every year they have a
new release. They call it the M1, the M2, the M2
Max, M23 Pro or whatever. And what they're doing
is they're actually studying what needs to be in
their microprocessor. And they add instructions
to their to their ARM systems based on what they
think we need we use these for, whether it's image
processing or audio or video or gaming or now
increasingly artificial intelligence. And one of
Apple's advantages is because they use the ARM and
they they license the core instruction set of the
ARM, but then they add their own instructions and
then manufacture them. Another thing about Apple
that's kind of interesting is you've been using an
emulator, a code that's written in JavaScript that
makes it look like you can run 6502 processors.
Well, in 2005, as Apple was moving from Power PC
to Intel processors, they included a technology
called Rosetta 1. And then when they were moving
from Intel to ARM processors in 2020, they
included a technology they called Rosetta 2.
And of course, that's a reference to the Rosetta
Stone, a famous stone with that connected multiple
languages from sort of antiquity to uh Latinbased
languages. And so what Rosetta did in both cases,
it translated the machine code from a
previous computer to the modern one. And
the the interesting thing was is it would often
run because the modern processors they were they
were choosing whether it be the Intel initially
or ARM later, they were so fast that they could
emulate the previous generation processors
almost at the same speed as the hardware of
the previous generation. And so this really made
it a lot easier for those of us who were Apple
customers making a transition from architectures
which otherwise would have almost been impossible
um to go from from a major one major CPU
architecture to another architecture. So fun
aside, there is sort of this indirect connection
between the 6502 and the ARM. And ARM stands for
Acorn Risk Microprocessor. And it it was built in
Cambridge, England by Acorn. Um, and if you Acorn
originally built a thing called the BBC Micro,
which was a 6502based micro computer, more popular
in the UK. And so they decided they were going
to create a new microprocessor. So they knew a
lot about 6502. The goal was not to make a better
6502, but there was a lot of homage to the 6502
in the ARM. And so they used BBC micros to build
and simulate the ARM design. ARM one had 25,000
transistors. The 6502 had 4,500 transistors.
And the ARM one through whatever there's many
generations of ARMs. And they are the most widely
used processors in the world. And for a good time,
you can ask AI to make this historical leap
connection between the 6502 ARM and the Raspberry
Pi. And I have a picture of Sophie Wilson, one
of the architecture designers of the initial
ARM working at um Acorn, working on both the BBC
Micro and the building of the AR microprocessor.
[Music] [Applause] [Music]